<chapter xml:id="chapter-simplifying" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Simplifying Expressions</title>
	
<section xml:id="section-what-are-expressions">
	<title>What Are Expressions?</title>
	<!-- <p>TODO: Expression, Algebraic Expression, Simplify, Evaluate, Equation, Solving, Domain</p> -->

	<p>An <term>algebraic expression</term> is a quantity representing a real number which may include one or more <term>variables</term> holding place for real numbers with unspecified values. The following are algebraic expressions:
	<me>4x^2-2x+1,\quad 10^{x^2-y^2}, \quad \frac{9}{\sqrt{4-\theta^2}}.</me>
	We may <term>evaluate</term> algebraic expressions by replacing each variable with a chosen real number.</p>

	<example>
		<statement><p>Evaluating <m>4x^2-2x+1</m> at <m>x=-1</m> results in
		<me>4(-1)^2-2(-1)+1 = 4+2+1 =7.</me></p></statement>
	</example>

	<p>We often need to <term>simplify</term> algebraic expressions. What this means depends on the situation, but usually we perform all operations we can to obtain a reduced expression.</p>

	<example>
		<title>Expanding an Expression</title>
		<statement>
		<p>Simplifying <me>x (3y - 5z) + 2xz</me> might require <term>expanding</term> the product via distribution and combining any like terms. Let's do this, separating equal expressions with the equal sign and writing down the page so we can compare each step with the previous:
		<md>
			<mrow>x (3y - 5z) + 2xz \quad 
					&amp;= x(3y) - x(5z) +2xz</mrow>
			<mrow>	&amp;= 3xy - 5xz + 2xz</mrow>
			<mrow>	&amp;= 3xy + (2-5)xz</mrow>
			<mrow>	&amp;= 3xy -3xz.</mrow>
		</md></p></statement>
	</example>

	<remark xml:id="writing-simplifying-expressions">
		<title>Mathematical Exposition</title>
		<p>Evaluating or simplifying an expression requires writing a <alert>sequence of equal expressions separated by the equal sign <q><m>=</m></q>.</alert> This is a practice you should adhere to throughout your college mathematics courses.</p>
	</remark>
</section>

<section xml:id="section-domain-of-an-expression">
	<title>Domain of an Expression</title>

	<p>The <term>domain</term> of an expression is the set of all values the variables may take in the expression. For instance, <m>x=1</m> is not in the domain of <m>\frac{1}{x-1}</m> because evaluating at <m>x=1</m> would result in division by zero, which is undefined. (See <xref ref="warning-division-by-zero"/>.) There are two things to consider when determining the domain of an expression.
	<ol>
		<li><em>Algebraic Constraints:</em> What constraints must be placed on the variables to ensure the result is a sensible real number? For instance, we should avoid division by zero or square roots of negative numbers.</li>
		<li><em>Practical Constraints:</em> What constraints does the context or application put on the variables? For example, if a variable represents a measured length, then it would be reasonable to require it to only take positive values.</li>
	</ol>
	</p>
	<example>
		<title>Algebraic Constraints on Domain</title>
		<statement>
			<p>Find the domain of each algebraic expression
				<ol>
					<li><m>\displaystyle 4-x</m></li>
					<li><m>\displaystyle \sqrt{4-x}</m></li>
					<li><m>\displaystyle \frac{1}{\sqrt{4-x}}</m></li>
					<li><m>\displaystyle \frac{1}{\sqrt{4+x^2}}</m></li>
					<li><m>\displaystyle \frac{1}{x-y}</m></li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li><p>The operation of subtracting <m>x</m> from <m>4</m> 
						may be performed to any real number. Thus, the domain is the set of all real numbers which we could write as 
						<m>\mathbb{R}</m> or in interval notation as 
						<m>(-\infty,+\infty)</m>.</p>
					</li>
					<li><p>Since a square root is now involved, we must require 
						<m>4-x \geq 0</m>. Equivalently, 
						<m>4 \geq x</m>. Thus, the domain is the interval <m>(-\infty,4]</m>.</p>
					</li>
					<li><p>Additionally, we require that we never divide by zero. This requires <m>4-x \gt 0</m> and the domain is now the open interval <m>(-\infty,4)</m>.</p>
					</li>
					<li><p>As before, we require that <m>4+x^2 \gt 0</m>. But squaring any real number results in a non-negative quantity and adding <m>4</m> will guarantee the result is positive. Thus, the domain is the set of all real numbers <m>\mathbb{R} = (-\infty,+\infty)</m></p></li>
					<li><p>We require that <m>x-y \neq 0</m>. This means <m>x \neq y</m>. So the domain is the set of all points <m>(x,y)</m> in the coordinate plane with <m>x\neq y</m>.</p></li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Practical Constraints on Domain</title>
		<statement>
			<p>You are to make an open top rectangular box from a flat piece of <m>8 \times 11</m> inch cardboard. To do so, make equal length cuts at the corners to remove square pieces and then fold up the sides to make a box.
			<image source="images/simplifying/box" width="50%"></image>
			 Find an algebraic expression for the volume of the box involving the variable <m>x</m> representing the depth of the cuts at each corner. What is the domain of the expression?</p>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<ul>
					<li>The height of the box is determined by the depth of the cuts <m>x</m>.</li>
					<li>The width of the box is <m>11-2x</m> inches.</li>
					<li>The length of the box is <m>8-2x</m> inches.</li>
				</ul>
				So the volume is given by
				<me>x(11-2x)(8-2x)</me>
				As a purely algebraic expression, the domain is <m>\mathbb{R}</m> as there is nothing preventing us from evaluating the expression above at any real number <m>x</m>. However, the physical constraints require the cuts be no deeper than the halfway point on the shortest side. So, <m>0\lt x \lt 4</m> and the domain is the interval <m>(0,4)</m>.
				</p>
			</solution>
		</example>
	
		<warning xml:id="warning-domain-change">
			<title>Domain and Simplification</title>
			<p>Sometimes simplifying an expression will appear to change its domain. For example,
			<me>\frac{x^2-x}{x} = \frac{x(x-1)}{x} = x-1.</me>
			But this equation is only true for <m>x \neq 0</m> as the left side is not defined for <m>x=0</m>. Therefore, it is often necessary to state this along with the simplified expression as
			<me>\frac{x^2-x}{x} = x-1, \quad \text{for $x\neq 0$.}</me></p>
		</warning>
</section>

<section xml:id="section-polynomial-expressions">
	<title>Polynomial Expressions</title>
	<p>A <term>polynomial expression</term> is an algebraic expression that involves only addition, subtraction, multiplication of non-negative integer powers of some variable or variables. For instance  <me>2x^3-4x^2-2x+4</me> is a polynomial in a single variable <m>x</m>. The expression <me>4s^3 t^5 - s^2 t^3 + \sqrt{2} s t</me> is a polynomial in the two variables <m>s</m> and <m>t</m>. A polynomial consists of a number of <term>terms</term> that are being added. Each term has a <term>coefficient</term>, and in the case of a single variable, the exponent determines the <term>degree</term> of the term. For example, the terms of <m>2x^3-4x^2-2x+4</m> are 
		<ul>
			<li><m>2x^3</m> with a coefficient of <m>2</m> and degree <m>3</m> which we would call a <term>cubic term</term>.</li>
			<li><m>-4x^2</m> with a coefficient of <m>-4</m> and degree <m>2</m> which we would call a <term>quadratic term</term>.</li>
			<li><m>-2x = -2x^1</m> with a coefficient of <m>-2</m> and degree <m>1</m> which would be called a <term>linear term</term>.</li>
			<li><m>4 = 4x^0</m> is a <term>constant term</term> with a coefficient of <m>4</m> and degree <m>0</m>.</li>
		</ul>
	The term with the highest-degree is called the <term>leading term</term> of the polynomial. The coefficient of the leading term is the <term>leading coefficient</term> and its degree determines the <term>degree of the polynomial</term>. In our case, <m>2x^3-4x^2-2x+1</m> has leading term <m>2x^3</m> with leading coefficient <m>2</m> and degree <m>3</m>.</p>

	<p>When adding or subtracting polynomials, combine <term>like terms</term> in the expression. These are terms with the same variables and degree, but possibly different coefficients. For instance, the following involve like terms of <m>x^2</m>
	<me>3x^2 - 2x^2 + 7x^2 = (3-2+7)x^2 = 8x^2.</me></p>

	<p>To multiply, distribute all terms and then simplify by combining like terms. Remember that exponents add when multiplying
	<me>x^3(4x^5 + x^3 + x - 1) =4x^8 + x^6 + x^4 - x^3.</me>
	</p>

	<example>
		<title>Simplifying Polynomial Expressions</title>
		<statement>
			<p>Preform the indicated operations and simplify. Show your work as a sequence of equal expressions separated by the equal sign. Video solutions follow.</p>
			<ol>
				<li><m>(4x^2-2xy+5y^3)+(7x^2-2xy-6y)</m></li>
				<li><m>(\sqrt{2} x^5-7x^3+\pi x - 6)-(\sqrt{3} x^5 + 7x^3+\pi x + 6)</m></li>
				<li><m>2x^5(4x^2-7x+1)</m></li>
				<li><m>(2x^5-3)(4x^2+2)</m></li>
				<li><m>(x+y)^2</m></li>
				<li><m>(x-y)^2</m></li>
				<li><m>(x-y)(x+y)</m></li>
				<li><m>(4x^2-3)^2</m></li>
			</ol>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<video youtube="pXbJnCP_4yA"/>
		</solution>
	</example>
</section>

<section xml:id="section-factoring">
	<title>Factoring</title>

	<p>We often need to <term>factor</term> polynomial or other algebraic expressions. This means to rewrite sums and differences as a product. A <term>monomial</term> is a single term of a polynomial expression. When factoring polynomials, you might first look for the greatest common monomial of each term.</p>
	
	<example>
		<title>Factoring out a Monomial Term</title>
		<statement><p>Factor 
			<me>3x^3 y^3 - 9 x^2 y^5 + 12 x y^7.</me></p>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<p>Each term has at least one factor of <m>3</m>, one factor of <m>x</m>, and three factors of <m>y</m>. So we can factor the greatest common factor <m>3 x y^3</m>
			<men xml:id="eqn-factored-monomial">3x^3 y^3 - 9 x^2 y^5 + 12 x y^7 
					= 3xy^3\left(x^2-3xy^2+4y^4\right)</men>
			Mentally redistribute the right side of <xref ref="eqn-factored-monomial"/> to confirm the result is correct.</p>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<p>A common problem is factoring a quadratic trinomial of the form 
	<m>ax^2+bx+c</m>. My recommendation is using a little trial and error while trying to reverse FOIL'ing. (See <xref ref="example-FOIL"/>.)</p>

	<example>
		<title>Factoring a Trinomial</title>
		<statement><p>Factor
			<me>x^2-2 x-15.</me>
		</p></statement>
		<solution><p>
			The product of the first terms must give us <m>x^2 = x\cdot x</m>, so we start with
			<me>x^2-2 x-15 = (x - ??)(x-??).</me>
			The product of the last two must give us <m>-15</m>. Put aside the sign for a moment and consider all the integer factorization of <m>15</m>:
			<me>15 = 1\times 15, \quad 3\times 5.</me>
			Try each one, adjusting the sign of each term. For example, none of 
			<me>(x - 1)(x-15), \quad (x+1)(x-15), \quad (x-1)(x+15), \quad (x+1)(x+15)</me>
			could work. The outer and inner terms all require adding or subtracting <m>1x</m> and <m>15x</m> which will never result in our middle term of <m>-2x</m>. So let's try
			<me>(x\pm 3)(x \pm 5)</me>
			which looks more promising since <m>3x</m> and <m>5x</m> will combine with the right sign to get <m>-2x</m>. Think about each possibility of sign to conclude
			<me>x^2-2 x-15 = (x + 3)(x - 5).</me>
		</p>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<p>When the leading coefficient is not <m>a=1</m>, the possibilities increase. While there are nice methods for helping you factor, I still recommend trial and error.</p>

	<example>
		<title>Factoring a Trinomial</title>
		<statement><p>Factor
			<me>2 x^2-13 x+15.</me>
		</p></statement>
		<solution><p>
			The first term factors as <m>2x\cdot x</m>, so we start with
			<me>(2x - ??)(x - ??).</me>
			You should still consider the possibilities <m>15 = 1\times 15</m> and <m>15 = 3\times 5</m>, but observe now that the factor of <m>2</m> in the first term will double whatever we put in the second factor. I quickly ruled out using <m>15 = 1\times 15</m>. The remaining cases are of the form
			<me>(2x \pm 3)(x \pm 5), \quad (2x \pm 5)(x \pm 3).</me>
			Try each one by FOIL'ing to find
			<me>2 x^2-13 x+15 = (2x - 3)(x-5).</me>
		</p></solution>
	</example>

	<p>Look for special forms, like a <term>difference of squares</term>
	<men xml:id="equation-difference-of-squares">a^2 - b^2  = (a-b)(a+b)</men>
	or a perfect square
	<men xml:id="equation-perfect-square-plus">a^2 + 2 ab + b^2  = (a+b)(a+b) = (a+b)^2</men>
	<men xml:id="equation-perfect-square-minus">a^2 - 2 ab + b^2  = (a-b)(a-b) = (a-b)^2</men>
	</p>

	<example>
		<title>Factoring a Difference of Squares</title>
		<statement><p>Factor
			<me>x^6 - 4y^2.</me>
		</p></statement>
		<solution><p>
			Each term is a square
			<me>x^6 - 4y^2 = (x^3)^2 - (2 y)^2.</me>
			So that
			<men xml:id="eqn-factored-difference-squares">
				x^6 - 4y^2 = (x^3-2y)(x^3 + 2y).</men>
			Again, mentally distribute the right side of <xref ref="eqn-factored-difference-squares"/> to confirm the result is correct. 
		</p></solution>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Combining Methods</title>
		<statment><p>Factor
			<me>3 x^4+3 x^3-36 x^2.</me></p>
		</statment>
		<solution>
			<p>There is a common monomial factor of <m>3x^2</m>:
				<me>3 x^4+3 x^3-36 x^2 = 3x^2 (x^2+x-12).</me>
				Next, factor the quadratic
				<me>3 x^4+3 x^3-36 x^2 = 3x^2 (x-3)(x+4).</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</example>
	
	<example>
		<title>Combining Methods</title>
		<statment><p>Factor
			<me>x^4-10 x^2+9.</me></p>
		</statment>
		<solution>
			<p>This is like a quadratic if we think of the first term as <m>x^4 = (x^2)^2</m>.
			<md>
				<mrow>x^4-10 x^2+9 &amp;= (x^2)^2 -10x^2 + 9</mrow>
				<mrow>	 &amp;= (x^2-9)(x^2-1)</mrow>
				<mrow>   &amp;= (x-3)(x+3)(x-1)(x+1).</mrow>
			</md>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<p>By creatively <q>splitting</q> the middle term of a quadratic you can sometimes create interesting factoring opportunities. One such method is called <term>factoring by grouping</term>.</p>

	<example>
		<title>Factor by Grouping</title>
		<statement>
		<p>Factor
			<me>9x^2 + 18x+ 8,</me>
			by observing that <m>18 x = 6x + 12x</m>.
		</p>
		</statement>
		<solution><p>
			First, using the advice
			<me>9x^2 + 18x+ 8 = 9x^2 + 6x + 12x + 8.</me>
			Now the first two terms have a common factor of <m>3x</m> and the second two terms have a common factor of <m>4</m>.
			<me>9x^2 + 18x+ 8 = 3x(3x + 2) + 4(3x + 2).</me>
			Cool! Each term now has a factor <m>3x+2</m>, so that
			<me>9x^2 + 18x+ 8 = (3x+2)(3x+4).</me>
		</p></solution>
	</example>
</section>

<section xml:id="section-rational-expressions">
	<title>Rational Expressions</title>
	
	<p>A <term>rational expression</term> is a fraction involving polynomials, such as
	<me>\frac{4x^2-3x+2}{(4-x)^2}.</me>
	Being able to perform algebraic operations on these and similar expressions is essential to success in calculus. Because division is involved, the domain of the expression is restricted all values of the variable that do not result in division by zero. In the case of the example above, we must restrict the domain to <m>x\neq 4</m>, or in interval notation <m>(-\infty,4)\cup(4,+\infty)</m>.</p>
	
	<example>
		<title>Cancellation</title>
		<p>You may <em>cancel common factors</em>in a fraction
			<me>\frac{8x^2-4xy}{4x^2} = \frac{4x(2x-y)}{4x^2} =  \frac{4x(2x-y)}{4x\cdot x} = \frac{2x-y}{x}.</me>
			But you must <em>never cancel common terms</em>
			<me>\frac{y+4x}{4x} \quad \text{is not} \quad y + \frac{4x}{4x} = y+1.</me>
			Although the following is correct
			<me>\frac{y+4x}{4x} = \frac{y}{4x} + \frac{4x}{4x} = \frac{y}{4x} + 1.</me>
		</p>
	</example>
	
	<example>
		<title>Finding Domains of Rational Expressions</title>
		<statement>
			<p>Find the domain of each rational expression. Video solutions follow.
				<ol cols="2">
					<li><m>\frac{4x^3-2x^2+1}{2x^2+5}</m></li>
					<li><m>\frac{2x^3+8x^2}{2x^3+6x^2-8x}</m></li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<video youtube="lobTYwQMKmY"/>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Multiplication</title>
		<p>To multiply rational expressions, simply multiply their numerators and denominators together.
		
		<me>\frac{2x}{3y} \cdot \frac{z^2}{y} = \frac{(2x)(z^2)}{(3y)(y)} = \frac{2xz^2}{3y^2}.</me>
	</p></example>
		
	<example>
		<title>Multiplication</title>
		<p>If the numerator or denominator includes a sum or difference, then be sure to distribute carefully.
		<me>\frac{-3}{2x} \cdot \frac{x-2}{x+2} = \frac{-3(x-2)}{2x(x+2)} = \frac{-3x+6}{2x^2+4x}.</me>
		</p>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Addition</title>
		<p>To add two rational expressions, you must first find a common denominator by providing missing <em>factors</em> to each term.
			<md>
				<mrow>\frac{2}{x} + \frac{3}{x-1} 
				&amp;= \frac{2}{x} \cdot \frac{x-1}{x-1} + \frac{3}{x-1}\cdot \frac{x}{x}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{2(x-1)}{x(x-1)} + \frac{3x}{(x-1)x}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{2(x-1)+3x}{x(x-1)}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{2x-2+3x}{x(x-1)}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{5x-2}{x(x-1)}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{5x-2}{x^2-x}</mrow>
			</md>
		</p>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Subtraction</title>
		<p>Subtraction is similarly to addition, but remember to distribute the sign.
			<md>
				<mrow>\frac{4}{x^2-1}-\frac{2}{x+1}
					&amp;= \frac{4}{(x-1)(x+1)} - \frac{2}{x+1}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{4}{(x-1)(x+1)} - \frac{2}{x+1}\cdot \frac{x-1}{x-1}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{4}{(x-1)(x+1)} - \frac{2(x-1)}{(x-1)(x+1)}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{4-2(x-1)}{(x-1)(x+1)}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{4-2x+2}{(x-1)(x+1)}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{6-2x}{(x-1)(x+1)}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{-2x+6}{x^2-1}</mrow>
			</md>
		</p>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Simplifying Rational Expressions</title>
		<statement>
			<p>Perform the indicated operation and simplify. Video solutions follow.</p>
			<ol>
				<li><p>Multiply 
					<m>\displaystyle \frac{-3}{x+2}\cdot \frac{4x+1}{x-2}</m>.</p>
				</li>
				<li><p>Subtract 
					<m>\displaystyle \frac{-3}{x+2}-\frac{4x+1}{x-2}</m>.</p>
				</li>
				<li><p>Add 
					<m>\displaystyle \frac{2x}{x^2-4}+\frac{3x}{2x+4}</m>.</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<video youtube="8pFJ2YzYI-M"/>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Dividing Rational Expressions</title>
		<p>To divide fractions, you could instead multiply by the reciprocal of the denominator. For example, let's perform the division
			
			<me>\frac{3}{x-1} \div \frac{1}{x+1}.</me>
			We have
			<md>
				<mrow>\frac{3}{x-1} \div \frac{1}{x+1}
				= \frac{\frac{3}{x-1}}{\frac{1}{x+1}}
				&amp;= \frac{3}{x-1}\cdot \frac{x+1}{1}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{3(x+1)}{x-1} </mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{3x+3}{x-1} </mrow></md>
		</p>
	</example>
	<p>A <term>compound rational expression</term>
		is a rational expression involving multiple divisions within one ratio. We always want to simplify these into a simple rational expression.</p>

	<example>
		<title>Dividing Rational Expressions</title>
		<p>You may multiply top and bottom by the appropriate expression and distribute it through to <em>clear the fractions</em>. This is particularly useful when simplifying a compound rational expressions such as
		
			<me>\frac{1}{1+\left(\frac{x}{y}\right)^2}.</me>
			We have
		
			<md>
				<mrow>\frac{1}{1+\left(\frac{x}{y}\right)^2} &amp;= \frac{1}{1+\frac{x^2}{y^2}}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{1}{1+\frac{x^2}{y^2}} \cdot \frac{y^2}{y^2}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{y^2}{(1+\frac{x^2}{y^2})y^2}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{y^2}{y^2+\frac{x^2}{y^2}\cdot y^2}</mrow>
				<mrow>&amp;= \frac{y^2}{y^2+x^2}</mrow></md>
		</p>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Simplifying Rational Expressions</title>
		<statement>
			<p>Perform the indicated operation and simplify. Video solutions follow.</p>
			<ol>
				<li><p><m>\displaystyle \frac{x}{x-3}\div \frac{2}{3x+2}</m></p></li>
				<li><p><m>\displaystyle \frac{\frac{1}{x}+\frac{1}{y}}{\frac{1}{xy}}</m></p></li>
				<li><p><m>\displaystyle \frac{\frac{2}{x+1}-\frac{3}{x+2}}{x-1}</m></p></li>
			</ol>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<video youtube="OZclVqVc6ZY"/>
		</solution>
	</example>
</section>

<section xml:id="section-radical-expressions">
	<title>Radical Expressions</title>

	<p><term>Radical expressions</term> are algebraic expressions involving <m>n</m>-th roots. 
		See <xref ref="section-roots-radicals"/>.) 
		Often we want to reduce radical expressions involving powers. This can be done by recognizing powers of <m>n</m> under the radical first and then extracting the base outside the radical. For example, 
		<m>\sqrt[3]{32} = \sqrt[3]{2^3\cdot 2^2} = 2\sqrt[3]{2^2} = 2 \sqrt[3]{4}</m>. Care must be taken when dealing with even versus odd <m>n</m>-th roots. In particular, <m>\sqrt[n]{x^n} = \left|x\right|</m>, for <em>even</em> positive integers <m>n</m>. See <xref ref="principle-properties-of-radicals"/>. </p>
	
	<example>
		<title>Reducing Radical Expressions (Even)</title>
		<p>
			Reduce the radical expression, keeping in mind that the <m>x</m> could be negative.
			<me>\sqrt[4]{32 x^6} = \sqrt[4]{2^4 \cdot 2 \cdot x^4 \cdot x^2} = 2 |x| \sqrt[4]{2 x^2}.</me>
			You can see the need for absolute value by considering a negative example of say <m>x=-1</m>. In this case,
			<me>\sqrt[4]{32 (-1)^6} = \sqrt[4]{32} = 2 \sqrt[4]{2}</me>
			must be positive. Without out the absolute value, it would not be.
		</p>
	</example>

<!-- 	
	<example>
		<title>Reducing Radical Expressions</title>
		<statement>
		<p>Reduce each radical expression, being considerate of the domain.
		<ol>
			<li>
				<p><m>\displaystyle \sqrt{72 x^{11} y^6}</m></p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p><m>\displaystyle \sqrt[3]{72 x^{11} y^6}</m></p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p><m>\displaystyle \sqrt[4]{72 x^{11} y^6}</m></p>
			</li>
		</ol>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<ol>
				<li>
					<p><m>\displaystyle \sqrt{72 x^9 y^6}</m>. Observe that <m>x\geq 0</m>, for otherwise the expression under the radical would be negative and that's undefined for a square root. On the otherhand, <m>y</m> may be any real number since <m>y^6 \geq 0</m> is always the case.
					<md>
						<mrow>&amp;=  \sqrt{8\cdot 9 \cdot x^{11} y^6}</mrow>
						<mrow>&amp;=  \sqrt{2^2 \cdot 2 \cdot 3^2 \cdot \left(x^5\right)^2 \cdot x \cdot \left(y^3\right)^2}</mrow>
						<mrow>&amp;=  2 \cdot 3 \cdot x^5 \left|y\right|^3\sqrt{ 2 x}</mrow>
					</md></p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p><m>\displaystyle \sqrt[3]{72 x^9 y^6}</m></p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p><m>\displaystyle \sqrt[4]{72 x^9 y^6}</m></p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</solution>
	</example>
 -->
	<example>
		<title>Reducing Radical Expressions (Odd)</title>
		<p>
			Reduce the radical expression, keeping in mind that the <m>x</m> could be negative.
			<me>\sqrt[3]{32 x^4} = \sqrt[3]{2^3 \cdot 2^2 \cdot x^3 \cdot x} = 2 x \sqrt[3]{4x}.</me>
		</p>
	</example>
		
	<p>Another common technique is to multiply by a form of one to rearrange radical expressions. For instance, it's common to remove square roots from the denominator (or numerator) by multiplying by a <term>form of one</term>
	<me>\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} \times {\color{blue}\frac{\sqrt{2}}{\sqrt{2}}} = \sqrt{2}{(\sqrt{2})^2} = \frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}.</me>
	This process is called <term>rationalizing</term> the denominator. We can use something similar when working with algebraic expressions involving radicals.</p>
	
	<example>
		<title>Addition with Radicals</title>
			<p>Consider the sum
			<me>\frac{\sqrt{1-x^2}}{x}+\frac{2}{\sqrt{1-x^2}}</me></p>
			<p>Find a common denominator to make the addition possible.
				<md>
					<mrow>\frac{\sqrt{1-x^2}}{x}+&amp;\frac{2}{\sqrt{1-x^2}}</mrow>
					<mrow>&amp;= \frac{\sqrt{1-x^2}}{x} \cdot {\color{blue}\frac{\sqrt{1-x^2}}{\sqrt{1-x^2}}} + \frac{2}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} \cdot {\color{blue}\frac{x}{x}} </mrow>
					<mrow>&amp;= \frac{(\sqrt{1-x^2})^2+2x}{x\sqrt{1-x^2}}</mrow>
					<mrow>&amp;= \frac{1-x^2+2x}{x\sqrt{1-x^2}}</mrow>
					<mrow>&amp;= \frac{-x^2+2x+1}{x\sqrt{1-x^2}}</mrow>
				</md>
			Note that you may <em>not</em> cancel the factor of <m>x</m> in the denominator as it is not a factor of the numerator.</p>
	</example>

	<example>
		<title>Multiplication with Radicals</title>
		<statement>
			<p>The expression below looks complicated.
				<me>\frac{\sqrt{2x-y}-2}{2x-y-4}\cdot \frac{\sqrt{2x-y}+2}{\sqrt{2x-y}+2}</me>
			But multiplication results in a difference of squares (see <xref ref="equation-difference-of-squares"/>) in the numerator. Observe the difference in sign and the cancellation of the middle terms.		
				<md>
					<mrow>\frac{\sqrt{2x-y}-2}{2x-y-4}\cdot &amp; \frac{\sqrt{2x-y}+2}{\sqrt{2x-y}+2}</mrow>
					<mrow>&amp;= \frac{\left(\sqrt{2x-y}\right)^2+{\color{blue} 2\sqrt{2x-y}}-{\color{blue}2\sqrt{2x-y}}-2^2}{\left(2x-y-4\right)\left(\sqrt{2x-y}+2\right)}</mrow>
					<mrow>&amp;= \frac{{\color{green} 2x-y-4}}{\left({\color{green}2x-y-4}\right)\left(\sqrt{2x-y}+2\right)}</mrow>
					<mrow>&amp;= \frac{1}{\sqrt{2x-y}+2}</mrow>
				</md></p>
		</statement>
	</example>

	<p>In the last example have multiplied the left factor by a <term>form of one</term> which leaves it unchanged.
	<me>\frac{\sqrt{2x-y}-2}{2x-y-4} = \frac{\sqrt{2x-y}-2}{2x-y-4} \cdot \frac{\sqrt{2x-y}+2}{\sqrt{2x-y}+2} = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2x-y}+2}</me>
	This is a useful technique used in calculus also referred to <term>rationalizing</term>.</p>

	<example>
		<title>Rationalizing the Numerator</title>
		<statement>
			<p>Rationalize the numerator and simplify
				<me>\frac{\sqrt{2+h}-\sqrt{2}}{h}.</me></p>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<md>
				<mrow>
					\frac{\sqrt{2+h}-\sqrt{2}}{h} &amp;</mrow>
				<mrow> &amp;= \frac{\sqrt{2+h}-\sqrt{2}}{h} \cdot \frac{\sqrt{2+h}+\sqrt{2}}{\sqrt{2+h}+\sqrt{2}}</mrow>
				<mrow> &amp;= \frac{2+h-2}{h\left(\sqrt{2+h}+\sqrt{2}\right)}</mrow>
				<mrow> &amp;= \frac{h}{h\left(\sqrt{2+h}+\sqrt{2}\right)}</mrow>
				<mrow> &amp;= \frac{1}{\sqrt{2+h}+\sqrt{2}}</mrow>
			</md>
		</solution>
	</example>
</section>

<section xml:id="section-exponential-expressions">
   	<title>Exponential Expressions</title>
   	<p>Recall that
   		<me>a^{-n} = \frac{1}{a}</me>
   		and
   		<me>a^{m/n} = \sqrt[n]{a^m} = \left(\sqrt[n]{a}\right)^m.</me>
   		(See <xref ref="chapter-exponents"/>.)
   		Calculus will require frequently moving between these exponential and algebraic forms.</p>

	<example>
		<title>Simplifying an Exponential Expression</title>
		<statement>
        <p>Assume <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are non-zero real numbers.
          <me>\left[ \left( \frac{-2x^{-1}y^2}{x^4 y^0} \right)^3 \right]^2.</me></p>
	  	</statement>
	    <solution>
        <p>One possible approach:
          <md>
            <mrow>\left[\left(\frac{-2x^{-1}y^2}{x^4 y^0}\right)^3\right]^2
                 &amp;= \left(\frac{-2x^{-1}y^2}{x^4 y^0}\right)^6</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= \left(\frac{-2y^2}{x \cdot x^4 \cdot 1}\right)^6</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= \left(\frac{-2y^2}{x^5}\right)^6</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= \frac{(-2)^6(y^2)^6}{(x^5)^6}</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= \frac{64 y^{12}}{x^{30}}</mrow></md>
        </p>
		</solution>
    </example>

    <example>
    	<title>Simplifying an Exponential Expression</title>
		<statement><p>Simplify the expression completely. Assume <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are positive real numbers.
          <me>\sqrt{9x^2 y^5} \sqrt{16 x^{-3} y}</me></p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>One possible approach is to express in terms of rational exponents and use the Laws of Exponents we've discussed.
          <md>
            <mrow>\sqrt{9x^2 y^5} \sqrt{16 x^{-3} y}
          &amp;= \left(9x^2 y^5\right)^{1/2} \left(16 x^{-3} y\right)^{1/2}</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= 3 x^1 y^{5/2} \cdot 4 x^{-3/2} y^{1/2}</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= 12 x^{1-3/2} y^{5/2+1/2}</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= 12 x^{-1/2} y^{3}</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= \frac{12 y^3}{x^{1/2}}</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;= \frac{12 y^3}{\sqrt{x}}</mrow></md>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

	<example>
      	<title>Simplifying an Exponential Expression</title>
      <statement>
        <p>Rewrite the expression in exponential notation using negative or rational powers of 
          <m>x</m>
          where appropriate.
      
          <me>4x^3 +\frac{2}{x^5} - \frac{1}{2x}+ \frac{3}{5 \sqrt{x}} + 2 \sqrt[4]{x^3} - 5</me></p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          <md>
            <mrow>4x^3 +\frac{2}{x^5} - \frac{1}{2x}+ \frac{3}{5 \sqrt{x}} + 2 \sqrt[4]{x^3} - 5</mrow>
            <mrow>=
          4x^3 +2x^{-5} - \frac{1}{2} x^{-1}+ \frac{3}{5} x^{-1/2} + 2 x^{3/4} - 5</mrow>Pay particular attention to how </md>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>
</section>

<xi:include href="../exercises/ex-simplifying.xml"/>
	

	<!-- <section>
		<title>Absolute Values</title>
		<p>Recall that the 
			<term>absolute value</term>
			<m>|x|</m>
			measures how far 
			<m>x</m>
			is from zero on the real line, i.e. the 
			<term>magnitude</term>
			of 
			<m>x</m>. We can express this formally with the conditional expression</p>
		<me>|x| = \begin{cases} 
				x, \quad &amp;\text{if $x \geq 0$}\\
				-x, \quad &amp; \text{if $x \lt 0$}
			\end{cases}</me>
		<example>
			<title>An absolute value expression</title>
			<p>I think we should be able to simplify the expression
				
				<me>\frac{|x-1|}{(x-1)^2}.</me>
				But it's just not possible without knowing more about the value of 
				<m>x</m>.  At the very least, we can assume 
				<m>x \neq 1</m>
				as this would result in division by zero and the expression is undefined. 
 			So let's think about what to do on either side of this value.</p>
			<p>If 
				<m>x \gt 1</m>
				then 
				<m>x -1 \gt 0</m>
				so that 
				<m>x-1</m>
				is positive. In this case,
 			
				<me>\frac{|x-1|}{(x-1)^2} = \frac{x-1}{(x-1)^2} = \frac{1}{x-1}.</me></p>
			<p>On the otherhand, if 
				<m>x \lt 1</m>
				then 
				<m>x -1 \lt 0</m>
				so that 
				<m>x-1</m>
				is negative. In this case, 
				<m>|x-1| = -(x-1)</m>
				and
 			
				<me>\frac{|x-1|}{(x-1)^2} = \frac{-(x-1)}{(x-1)^2} = \frac{-1}{x-1} = \frac{1}{1-x}.</me></p>
			<p>To summarize,
 			
				<me>\frac{|x-1|}{(x-1)^2} = \begin{cases} 
				\frac{1}{x-1}, \quad&amp; \text{if $x \gt 1$}\\
				\frac{1}{1-x}, \quad&amp; \text{if $x \lt 1$}\\
				\text{undef.}, \quad&amp; \text{if $x=1$}
			\end{cases}</me></p>
		</example>
	</section> -->

